Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is י"ב. yud-bet.
And we pick up at the bottom of י"א עמוד ב'. yud-aleph
amud-bet. And the גמרא Gemara and the Rami bar Chama asked a
question about if somebody says "this should be אסור asur to me
like the meat of a שלמים shelamim after זריקת הדם". zrikat hadam
After זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, a שלמים shelamim is permissible to be
eaten. So the גמרא Gemara says, so then what's the question? You're
very clear that you're not referring to something that is a דבר
הנדור davar hanadur that is forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara changes the
case to be one where there actually is the meat of a
שלמים shelamim after the blood has been thrown. And the guy's there
munching on his leg of lamb and he says by a piece
of bread, "זה כזה". zeh kazeh Okay, so this piece of bread
is like this leg of lamb here that I'm eating. And the
question is: does he refer to its current state where it's not
a דבר—where it's a דבר הנדור davar hanadur because it's a שלמים,
shelamim, but it's not a דבר הנדור davar hanadur. in an אסור
asur state, because he's—it's the blood has been thrown, he's מותר mutar
to eat from it and therefore it would not be a problem?
Or does he refer to its original state, בעיקרו קמתפיס, bikaro kamatpis,
which is as when he originally sanctified it as a שלמים shelamim
and then it's a forbidden thing as a דבר הנדור. davar hanadur,
So what's the story? So let's read that—well, I guess maybe we'll
four lines—let's maybe pick up four lines from the bottom on י"א
עמוד ב'. yud-aleph amud-bet. אי דקאמר בהדין לישנא בהדי קמתפיס. ee d'ka-amar
b'hadain lishana be-hedei kamatpis. אלא כגון דמנח בשרא דזבחי שלמים, ela k'gon
d'manach basra d'zivchei shelamim,
there's the meat of a זבחי שלמים, zivchei shelamim, which is permissible
to be eaten now, because it's meat, it isn't a live animal,
so obviously the blood's been thrown, ומחת דהתירא גביה, umachas de-heteira gabei,
and there's something else permissible next to him, a piece of bread,
loaf of bread. ואמר זה כזה. ve-amar zeh kazeh.
So this is like this. מאי? mai? בעיקרו קמתפיס? bikaro kamatpis?
What originally was, was a live animal walking around that was a—sanctified
as a שלמים shelamim and therefore אסור asur because it was before
it had become meat? או בהיתירא קמתפיס? o b'heteira kamatpis? Or is
it its current state where it's היתר heter and therefore it's not
a נדר? neder? אמר רבא: amar Rava: תא שמע, tashma, come and
hear. נותר ופיגול. notar u-pigul.
We have in our משנה Mishnah that a way you can make
a נדר neder is you say "הרי זה נותר הרי זה פיגול".
harei zeh notar, harei zeh pigul Okay? והא נותר ופיגול אחר זריקת
דמים
הוא.
ve-ha notar u-pigul achar zrikat damim
hu. Now the—something only becomes נותר—this notar isn't a piece of meat
in front of him, but it's describing the state of something, and
the state of something is נותר, notar, is the blood's been thrown,
you had a period where you were eating the meat, and then
you left the meat over for, you know, till after the morning—till
daybreak,
and now it's נותר. notar. So that is meat that was no
longer אסור asur for a period of time.
Now פיגול pigul never becomes מותר.
mutar. פיגול pigul because you had the thought of פיגול pigul when
you did the שחיטה shechita or when you did the זריקה, zrika,
it always remains אסור asur as it was. So פיגול pigul actually
is conceptually לפני זריקת דם, lifnei zrikat dam, even if it's לאחר
זריקת דם, l'achar zrikat dam, then it was a מתיר matir of
the זריקת דם. zrikat dam. So the ראשונים Rishonim take out the
word פיגול pigul or they say that it was לאו דוקא lav
davka to refer to the נותר notar question. So נותר, notar, you
sprinkle the blood, you were able to eat the meat, and then
because you left the meat over, it's forbidden. So there's an איסור
issur to eat it, it's an איסור נותר, issur notar, but that's
not an איסור issur of your נדר, neder, right? That's like, you
know, that's like an איסור issur of בשר בחלב. basar be-chalav. The
Torah made an איסור issur of נותר, notar, but it's not an
איסור issur that derives from your נדר neder because you actually were
a period where you were totally allowed to eat from it. So
that would be מתפיס בדבר האסור, matpis bedavar ha-asur, not מתפיס בדבר
הנדור. matpis bedavar hanadur. Its current state as שלמים shelamim meat that's
a נותר notar is only a forbidden state of something that the
Torah imposes on it and not a status of forbiddenness that derives
from your sanctifying it. You know, that's a direct effect of your
נדר. neder. So
therefore, yes, נותר notar meat is
forbidden and yes, it's a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur but
it is not forbidden because of the נדר. neder. Because of
the
נדר neder actually you were able to
eat from it, there was a
period you were מותר mutar to eat from it, and now this
status of נותר notar is seen as some new state. Okay. What?
So do you say
that it works? So therefore you see that you're referring not
to
its current state of
נותר... notar... But it is not forbidden because of the נדר. neder.
Because of the נדר neder actually you are able to eat from
it. There was a period you were מותר mutar to eat from
it and now this status of נותר nosar is seen as some
new state. Now, okay. What do you
say?
That it works. So therefore you see that you're referring not to
its current state of נותר, nosar, but you're referring to originally, נותר
nosar is labeling, identifying what object you're referring to, but what you
mean to do is relate to its status from before זריקת הדם.
zrika hadam. Okay. And therefore so that's a proof that when you
are referring to that object, even if right now it doesn't technically
fit in the box, if originally it did, then that's the, then
that's the status you're referring to.
Okay. Can you just remind us to clarify, פיגול pigul is a
matter of a מחשבה? machshava? Yes.
When you had a thought to either the wrong, the wrong time.
I mean, you might, you might end up eating it in the
right time, but the מחשבה machshava affects the status.
Exactly. So פיגול pigul is actually something that never had a זריקת
הדם zrika hadam that made it permissible because your thoughts was wrong
at
the time before.
Exactly. So אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב נתן, amar lei Rav
Huna brei d'Rav Nasan, בנותר של עולה. b'nosar shel olah. We wouldn't
be talking about any נותר nosar or maybe
you know there's always a question of סתם נדרים להחמיר, stam nedarim
l'hachmir, that since there exists an example
of נותר nosar that the thing never became permissible to be eaten,
which is an עולה. olah. Even after זריקת הדם, zrika hadam, an
עולה olah can't be eaten, it's forbidden, and it's forbidden as a
result of the נדר. neder. So the נותר nosar element is not
what makes it forbidden, right? So the נותר, nosar, it was always
forbidden as a result of your נדר. neder. So it could be
either you explicitly said, הרי זה נותר של עולה, harei zeh nosar
shel olah, or you just said הרי זה נותר, harei zeh nosar,
but since there's a type of a נותר nosar when סתם נדרים
להחמיר, stam nedarim l'hachmir, there's a type of a נותר nosar that's
always אסור assur as a דבר הנדור davar hanadur, without ever having
become מותר, mutar, which is the
case of עולה, olah, that's the way in which we'll interpret it.
But if you explicitly said like הרי זה נותר של שלמים, harei
zeh nosar shel shelamim, okay, we would say, no, then we'll interpret
your words as based on its current state and its current state
is not forbidden as a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur. yes.
Why would you have to label the עולה olah as a נותר
nosar since it's forbidden?
Ah, excellent question. That's what the גמרא gemara asks. So אמר ליה,
amar lei, אם כן, im kein, לישני בבשר עולה, lisnei b'vesar olah,
right? Why didn't you just say עולה? olah? Why didn't you say
בשר עולה? basar olah? I mean why did you say נותר של
עולה? nosar shel olah? Just say בשר עולה. basar olah. לא
מיבעיא קאמר,
lo mibaya
ka'amar, it goes without saying. לא מיבעיא בשר עולה, lo mibaya basar
olah, if you say הרי זה עולה, harei zeh olah, דאסור, d'assur,
דבקרבן קא מתפיס, d'b'korban ka matpis, there's no question that you're referring
to the status of something as a קרבן, korban, as a דבר
הנדור. davar hanadur.
But נותר פיגול דעולה, nosar pigul d'olah, if you said נותר פיגול
nosar pigul of עולה, olah, we're again bracketing פיגול, pigul, איצטריך. itztrich.
It's a חידוש. chidush. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, I would
have thought, כי איסור
נותר כי איסור פיגול, k'issur nosar k'issur pigul, הוה ליה כמתפיס בדבר
האסור, hvei lei k'matpis b'davar ha'assur, even though נותר nosar of an
עולה olah is אסור assur because it's an עולה, olah, but it
also has a status of נותר. nosar. And since you bothered to
say נותר, nosar, maybe you meant to make your bread like the
איסור issur aspect of נותר, nosar, not the נדר neder aspect of
נותר. nosar. Let's say you said, הרי זה כבשר בחלב harei zeh
k'basar b'chalav that was made with the meat of an עולה. olah.
Okay, so right, let's just say you said that. So, would we
say oh, you're מתפיס בדבר הנדור? matpis b'davar hanadur? It says no,
I mean okay for some bizarre reason you mentioned the meat of
an עולה, olah, but what you're talking about is its status as
בשר בחלב. basar b'chalav. And its status as בשר בחלב basar b'chalav
is not a דבר הנדור. davar hanadur Okay, so if you said
נותר של עולה, nosar shel olah, maybe you're referring to its נותר
nosar status, which is not a status of איסור issur based on
the נדר neder per se. So therefore I would think that it's
מותר, mutar, so הוה ליה כמתפיס בדבר האסור hvei lei k'matpis b'davar
ha'assur ולא מתפיס, v'lo matpis, קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, that
no, that because you are still referring to something that is an
עולה olah and it never got a היתר, heter, so נותר nosar
is a way of emphasizing the איסור issur status of it, but
nevertheless you are and again it's not like if you said בשר
בחלב basar b'chalav of עולה olah presumably I would guess it actually
would be מותר, mutar, because here נותר nosar is deeply intertwined with
its קרבן korban status, right? So clearly you are referring so we
say in the end of the day you're referring to its איסור
issur status based on a דבר הנדור davar hanadur, not on a
דבר האסור. davar ha'assur. Although again it's not clear to me just
one second whether you're explicitly saying
הרי זה כנותר של עולה harei zeh k'nosar shel olah or you
just said הרי זה נותר harei zeh nosar and since there exists
נותר של עולה nosar shel olah we interpret it in the more
strict way. Yes, Zev.
So maybe this discussed already, so we can move it by later,
but I understand when we talk about the different לשונות leshonos and
what their meanings are, but when we're talking about like what did
you intend when you said this, which is more what we're getting
into now, why wouldn't you just ask the person? Why are we
guessing at that question?
Yeah, so that's like always the question. So I think what I
would answer is, is that you know what we're always saying which
is, it doesn't matter what you intended, it matters what you said,
and therefore what did you say? I mean if a statement has
multiple meanings, so what this is really an assessment of is like
how are we going to choose what the, so how to interpret
what it is that you said. You know,
so, I mean let's say for example,
you know, there's like a story right where like somebody,
there was like a playwright wrote this play and they were putting
it up. and it was first time that it went on and
like everybody was like was laughing. And it was a question like
had he meant it as a comedy? So the guy said did
you mean this as a comedy? He says if they think it's
a comedy it's a comedy. You know, so if basically let's say
the guy was like we were reading a piece of literature and
the author wasn't around and it didn't matter what the author meant.
Question's well what do the words say? That seems to be the
focus of this מסכת. Masechet. So it would be very nice if
you told us what you meant, but in order for it to
be a נדר, Neder, it's not enough what you mean, it's what
you say. Now, you know, so yet again, if you say, if
you said, like the questions did come up, well how about if
there's like context? And the גמרא Gemara will talk about context. If
somebody was saying this to a person and the person responded, what
about tone of voice? That's interesting that the גמרא Gemara like you
know will get a little bit of that later but the גמרא
Gemara doesn't really you know get to that issue. But those are
types of things which like we don't have to guess what's in
your mind based on the evidence in front of us we're going
to assess what meaning is. So that seems to me the issue
about all of this, you know, yeah.
I think that maybe the problem is that like our mindset is,
you know,
you're not going to go ask the רב Rav what did I
mean. You're going to ask him, you know, what did I refer
to in this thing here. Here the גמרא Gemara is like telling
you what you meant. And it's more...
Well look, first of all, an important thing to realize is that
you can make it אסור assur not just on yourself. You can
make it אסור assur on somebody else. So let's say the guy
said, הרי זה כנותר, harei zeh kenosar, הרי זה נותר, harei zeh
nosar,
you know, my food is עליך נותר. alecha nosar. And then I
went away and I'm now in my favorite place, I'm in Hawaii.
Okay? And you have to know. So, right? So you can't ask
me. So it's a question of defining what it meant, right? So
even if I go to the rabbi and I say I made
I said these are the words I said,
and here's what I meant, the rabbi could say I don't really
care what you meant. You didn't say the right words, you didn't
say words הלכה Halacha would define as meaning X. So even if
you meant X, those aren't the words you said and therefore it
doesn't have a Halachic effect. Right?
Yeah, so it returns to the fact like I said with you
know words like you know כקונם kikonam or whatever. But yeah, with
what you said about other people, that...
Right,
so my point is even if it's truly true about other people
that we could just say well we have to go by what
you said, it's even going to be true about yourself. You need
to say the right words in order to have it have an
effect and it doesn't really matter that you know what you meant.
Yes, Dov.
Two things. One is, this is profoundly contemporary in terms of reader
theory. The words are out there. Once the words are out there,
their meaning is in the hearer or in the reader.
Or here some question of the legal meaning of it.
Right. As opposed to the original intent of the author. So this
is a phenomenally contemporary.
I have a question also about the whole thing about פיגול pigul
and נותר. nosar. Is he... is the person making the נדר Neder
talking about that piece of meat or making an analogy to some
other food may it be אסור assur by my נדר Neder as
if like the way this is אסור assur as an עולה? olah?
Right, so the case of פיגול pigul of נותר nosar of פיגול
pigul and נותר, nosar, we don't have it's like it's not the
שלמים shelamim case, this is actually a piece of meat in front
of you. You just said by a piece of bread, a loaf
of bread, הרי זה נותר harei zeh nosar or הרי זה נותר
של עולה. harei zeh nosar shel olah. Okay? But conceptually, נותר nosar
is not a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur at least its status as
איסור issur is not a דבר הנדור davar hanadur unless we're talking
about נותר של עולה. nosar shel olah. So that's right...
exactly, exactly. And we're trying to say בעיקרו כמתפיס be'ikaro kamatpis as
opposed to בהיתירו כמתפיס.
behaitero kamatpis. דבר הנדור davar hanadur? versus דבר האסור. davar ha'assur. Do
we say that since I can make this an עולה, olah, like
that's why it's a דבר הנדור?
davar hanadur Yeah, דבר הנדור davar hanadur, meaning it gets its status
through a speech act, yeah.
Oh, meaning not because I make it a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur
meaning like me personally like I have that power to do it.
In other words, wouldn't make a difference if
I say like
like
קרבן תמיד, korban tamid, right? Because I'm not נודר noder a קרבן
תמיד. korban tamid. It wouldn't make a difference, right?
Correct, it's a status that comes... okay, two last questions and then
we gotta move on. Yeah.
Are you making a distinction between intent in terms of the necessity
for intent that we discussed
earlier that along with saying it properly you also have to have
the intent?
That is correct, but that's what I'm doing is, there's two things.
I mean and again it's we're I I you know like I
understand that this is a question it keeps on being coming up
again, which is you do need to have the right intent, okay,
עד שפיו ולבו שוין. ad she-piv ve-libo shavin. Okay, but intent is
not really used or accessed in order to define what you said.
You also have to have said the right thing. Right.
So Dov's question was why not to determine what you said don't
we ask you what you meant? And what I'm saying is no
because we have to assess what you said independent of what might
have been going on in your head. We just have to look
at those words and assess them.
But if you had said the proper word...
then we also do care what you... yes, that is correct. Can
I say something?
Trying to understand what the קא משמע לן kamashma lan is. I
might have thought by נותר nosar and פיגול דעולה pigul de-olah what
I might have thought... I'm not clear to me what the קא
משמע לן kamashma lan is.
קא משמע לן kamashma lan that when you say that הרי זה
כנותר של עולה, harei zeh ke-nosar shel olah, let's say you said
that explicitly, you're referring still to its עולה olah status as a
דבר הנדור davar hanadur. and not to its איסור issur status as
נותר nosar and therefore it's אסור. assur. If I said הרי זה
כבשר בחלב של עולה harei zeh ke-basar be-chalav shel olah would that
be מתיר? matir? מתפיס בדבר האסור matpis b'davar ha'assur or מתפיס בדבר
הנדור? matpis b'davar hanadur? It's the
דבר האסור. davar ha'assur. Okay, so maybe the same should be when
I say הרי זה כנוסו של עולה, harei zeh kinuso shel olah,
because the נותר nosar status is an איסור issur status, it's not
something that's a direct result of my נדר. neder.
And when he just said עולה? olah?
Obviously that's a דבר הנדור. davar hanadur נותר nosar might mean דבר
האסור. davar ha'assur.
And maybe he meant נותר nosar as that, no, that's the point.
You said נותר nosar but if you totally emphasized the נותר nosar
aspect of it, then it's a דבר האסור. davar ha'assur. But a
נותר של עולה notar shel olah, also happens to be an עולה
olah and therefore that's the חידוש chiddush that you're relating to its
דבר הנדור davar hanadur? status.
All right, we'll go on. All right, you have to think about
that. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. מיתיבי, Meiseiv,
I'll ask you on this.
איזו איסור האמור בתורה, Eizo issur ha'amur b'Torah, what is a forbidden
status set in the Torah? It's a funny phrase where I had
that introduction. But anyway,
אמר, Amar, הריני שלא אוכל בשר, Harei ni shelo ochal basar, behold
I am that I won't eat meat, ושלא אשתה יין, v'shelo eshteh
yayin, and I won't drink
wine, כיום שמת בו אביו, k'yom shemeis bo aviv, like on the
day that his father died. So you have this idea by the
way of accepting like a תענית ta'anis or certain types of you
know, sort of types of self-denial whatever on a יארצייט, Yahrtzeit, you
know goes way back. Okay. Or כיום שמת בו רבו, k'yom shemeis
bo rabbo, like the day his Rebbe died. I will explain it.
כיום שנהרג בו גדליה בן אחיקם, k'yom sheneherag bo Gedaliah ben Achikam,
or you decided that it wasn't enough that חז״ל Chazal had this
תענית, ta'anis, you wanted to add your own נדר neder to it,
which is interesting. או כיום שראיתי ירושלים בחורבנה, O k'yom sheraiti Yerushalayim
b'churbana, or like the day when I went to visit Yerushalayim and
I saw that it was destroyed. Okay, now what does that mean?
It means that presumably,
well that's going to be the line that שמואל Shmuel says, ואמר
שמואל והוא שנדר באותו היום. V'amar Shmuel v'hu shenadar b'oso hayom. So
basically what it means is this guy five years ago on when
his father died, he accepted a תענית. ta'anis. And now it's five
years later and he says הרי עלי, harei alai, I am accepting
upon myself a נדר neder not to eat meat like I did,
like that נדר neder I accepted upon myself, that status I accepted
upon myself five years ago when my father died. That's what he
said. Or five years ago he visited Yerushalayim and it was בחורבנה
b'churbana and he took a נדר, neder, and now it's five years
later and he's saying I'm taking a נדר neder like that, so
he's מתפיס בדבר הנדור. matpis b'davar hanadur. What's the דבר הנדור? davar
hanadur, The נדר neder that he had made five years ago. He's
piggybacking that נדר neder that I made five years ago, that status
should be applied to this. Now the question is what's the this
first of all? I mean what's the object here? Is it me,
הריני? hareini? I'm a דבר האסור? davar ha'assur? Right? Again this you
know again we get this like confusion of the idea of it
sounds more like a שבועה, shvuah, I'm promising not to do it
the same way I won't. But what it does seem actually and
we'll get to this, you know we discussed before that צדקה tzedakah
is a type of a נדר neder because like you know you
a you take a vow, so that's like נדרי מצוה, nidrei mitzvah,
you make a commitment to give צדקה tzedakah and then you set
aside the money and that gets its status as צדקה. tzedakah. Well
the other thing that's not that's another religious phenomenon that's like a
נדר neder or in the נדר neder category is a תענית. ta'anis.
When somebody says הריני בתענית היום, hareini b'ta'anis hayom, right? You know
or when the person says the התרת נדרים Hataras Nedarim and you
say I'm saying now that any נדר neder that I make won't
be effective on me חוץ מנדרי תענית בשעת מנחה, chutz minidrei ta'anis
b'sha'as mincha, some people say אפילו בנדרי תענית בשעת מנחה. afilu binidrei
ta'anis b'sha'as mincha. But the point is accepting upon yourself to do
a תענית, ta'anis, right? There's a similar idea to like the idea
of accepting upon yourself to give צדקה. tzedakah. Now what is though
the object? Like צדקה tzedakah you set aside the money at the
end. What is the object at the end? The object at the
end might be here the day. Okay. We might have the conceptual
identity of the day, that the day becomes has the same way
money has the status of צדקה tzedakah and the bread should have
a status of קונם, konam, the day can have a status of
תענית. ta'anis. I could give the day an איסור issur status. Okay.
So that seems to be the conceptual model by a תענית. ta'anis.
So five years ago I said this day is אסור עלי assur
alai presumably we're talking about the identity of the day, this day
is
אסור עלי assur alai that I won't eat meat or drink wine.
So that now becomes like the identity of the day. Okay. And
I made that through a נדר. neder. Now five years from now
I'm saying this day is like that day five years ago. So
that day five years ago was a day that was אסור assur
through a נדר neder that I made and I'm מתפיס matpis this
day with that day. That's the conceptual model. Wait wait let's read
a little bit more. Okay. So somebody said that or five years
ago when it was צום גדליה, Tzom Gedaliah, he said even though
he was already אסור בתענית assur b'ta'anis which is a point that
we'll get to, he you know he made it אסור assur also
מצד mitzad his נדר. neder. If he had never taken a נדר
neder on that צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah five years ago and said
today is like צום גדליה, Tzom Gedaliah, well צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah
isn't a day that's a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur. it's a day
you have to do because because it's a תענית דרבנן. ta'anis d'rabbanan.
But it happened to be five years ago you added your own
נדר neder to צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah and now you're saying today
is like that צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah five years ago that I
had made אסור assur on myself as a נדר. neder. So you're
מתפיס בדבר matpis b'davar and שמואל Shmuel says, והוא שנדר באותו היום,
v'hu shenadar b'oso hayom,
the day you're standing on today is the same day as five
years ago.
Okay, meaning it's
also צום גדליה, Tzom Gedaliah, it's also your, you know, your father's
יארצייט, yortzeit, okay. היכי דמי, Heichi dami,
what's the case? לאו כגון דקאי בחד בשבתא, lav k'gon d'kai b'chad
b'shabta, בשבתא, b'shabta,
you're on Sunday now, the תוספות Tosafos says we don't mean Sunday,
we mean let's say the same the same calendar day, okay. You're
on the third of תשרי, Tishrei, you're on צום גדליה, Tzom Gedaliah,
you're on the tenth of סיון, Sivan, which is the guy which
is the, you know, the father's יארצייט. yortzeit. Okay, דקאי בחד בשבתא
דמיית ביה אבוה, d'kai b'chad b'shabta d'meis bei avuh, that's his father's
יארצייט, yortzeit, ואף על גב דאיכא טובא חד בשבתא דאיתירו, v'af al
gav d'ika tuva chad b'shabta d'ateiru, even though there were many יארצייטס
yortzeits between that original day that the father died and today, it
was five years ago. So the נדר neder you made was five
years ago. And you're right now here on, you know, the tenth
of סיון, Sivan, and you say הרי זו עלי harei zu alai
like the like my father's יארצייט, yortzeit, okay, that's what the guy
said, okay. Or הרי זו עלי כצום גדליה. harei zu alai k'Tzom
Gedaliah. And there were four יארצייטס yortzeits and four צום גדליה'ס Tzom
Gedaliahs that were immediately past that were not a דבר הנדור. davar
hanadur, To get to the one that was a דבר הנדור, davar
hanadur, you had to go five years back. And nevertheless, when you
say הרי זו עלי כצום גדליה, harei zu alai k'Tzom Gedaliah, הרי
זו עלי harei zu alai like my father's יארצייט, yortzeit, we say
you're referring to the נדר neder status of your father's יארצייט, yortzeit,
the נדר neder status of צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah that occurred five
years ago, not the most four recent צום גדליה'ס Tzom Gedaliahs or
father's יארצייטס. yortzeits. So that's a proof that we say you go
מעיקרו קמתפיס, me'ikaro kamatpis, you go back to something's original state. Again,
fascinating how we're abstracting, right, the idea of a day, right, to
make a day אסור asur as a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, you
could sort of see it the same way a קרבן korban changes
its status. So this שלמים shlamim used to be a דבר הנדור,
davar hanadur and now the שלמים shlamim became a דבר המותר davar
hamutar after זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. This day of my father's יארצייט
yortzeit used to be a דבר הנדור davar hanadur. and then when
it rolls around next year, it's like it's the same day with
now a new status, right? And when I'm now saying five years
from now, am I going on the status that this day had
in its instantiation five years ago or am I going on the
status of this day in its instantiation the last four years. Very
fascinating, right, the way we're concretizing this abstract idea. So anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says that doesn't that show you מעיקרו קמתפיס. me'ikaro
kamatpis. וקתני אף על גב דאיכא טובא חד בשבתא דאיתירו, v'katani af
al gav d'ika tuva chad b'shabta d'ateiru, even though there were many,
you know, יארצייטס yortzeits that occurred in between, four years, right, וקתני
אסור, v'katani asur, nevertheless it says it's אסור. asur. שמע מינה בעיקר
הוא מתפיס, shma mina b'ikar hu matpis, you say you go back
to the original state. So the גמרא Gemara says no, דשמואל הכי
איתמר. d'Shmuel hachi ismar. Here's how you have to read שמואל. Shmuel.
אמר שמואל והוא שנדר ובא מאותו היום ואילך, Amar Shmuel v'hu shenadar
u'va m'oso hayom v'eilech, that it's been ongoing, that for the last
five years since the day of your father's death, you've been doing
a תענית ta'anis every single יארצייט. yortzeit. Okay, so when you say
this is like my father's יארצייט, yortzeit, all the days are דבר
הנדור. davar hanadur Now of course, you know, well this is like
צום גדליה, Tzom Gedaliah, since five years ago, all your צום גדליה'ס
Tzom Gedaliahs you've made אסור asur on yourself as a נדר. neder.
So תוספות Tosafos says well maybe you meant the צום גדליה Tzom
Gedaliah from before five years ago? Maybe you meant this day before
your father died? No, that's like that's clearly not even part of
the conversation, right? That's not in the context of the words that
I'm saying. So since so, so therefore, in that, so that, so
therefore, we don't have a case where the day conceptually went from
being a דבר הנדור davar hanadur to an interim where it's דבר
המותר davar hamutar and now which status are you referring to? The
entire last history of the day had been completely always with that
status. You made a נדר neder every year. Every year, exactly. Exactly.
Exactly. Exactly. So that's a good question what exactly the חידוש chiddush
is. So the ר"ן Ran discusses what the חידוש chiddush is on.
You could say the חידוש chiddush is that we concretize the idea
of a day and you could turn a day into something that
you can make a נדר neder about. But the גמרא Gemara in
שבועות Shevuos where this occurs says that the חידוש chiddush is that
you can make a נדר neder on a day that's already אסור
מדרבנן. asur m'drabanan. Right? You can't make a נדר neder on something
that's already אסור. asur. If this is בשר בחלב, basar b'chalav, right?
It's sort of like, you know, שבועה חלה על שבועה, shevua chala
al shevua, נדר חל על נדר, neder chal al neder, whatever. So
or maybe you can't, I mean, we'll see about that. But anyway,
let's just take a look at this, let me just read this
entire thing and then I'll take all the questions. So if you
take a look two lines in the ר"ן Ran near the end
of the line, he quotes the גמרא Gemara in שבועות, Shevuos, it
says, ומקשינן הנא נמי פשיטא. u'makshinan hana nami peshita. The שבועות Shevuos
I'm reading. The ר"ן, Ran, it's in the middle of it, two
lines in the wide lines, middle of the line, he says, ומקשינן,
u'makshinan, right before like the column between the ר"ן Ran and the
רש"י, Rashi, or right after. ומקשינן הנא נמי פשיטא, u'makshinan hana nami
peshita, מהו דתימא מכיון דאפילו לא נדר אסור מדרבנן, mahu d'teima mikeivan
d'afilu lo nadar asur m'drabanan, כי נדר נמי לא חייל נדר, ki
nadar nami lo chayil neder, maybe since the צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah
is already אסור מדרבנן asur m'drabanan it won't the נדר neder won't
take effect, ולא מתפיס בנדר הוא, v'lo matpis b'neder hu, קא משמע
לן ka mashma lan that it does. Okay. And then he says,
so that's the חידוש. chiddush. And then he gives an interesting practical
implication about this, he says, okay, ומה שכתב. u'ma shekasav. About three
lines from the bottom now in the same רן Ran *Ran* or
four lines from the top of the widest line, yeah, the widest
line where it says וממסקנא דסוגיא דשבועות שמעינן *u'mimaskana d'sugya d'shavuos shmeinan*
לנודר מגבינה של נכרים וסתם יינם ושומנו של גיד *l'noder mi'gvina shel
nochrim v'stam yeinam v'shumano shel gid*, so I don't know if he's
saying this just because it's an interesting hypothetical or because whether maybe
people actually did it. So here are some classic examples of things
that are אסור assur. דרבנן *assur d'rabbanan*, right, גבינה *gvina* of non-Jews,
Kraft cheese, okay, or סתם יינם *stam yeinam*, or the fat of
a גיד הנשה *gid hanasheh*, okay. And so you said, even though
it was already אסור assur *assur* to you מדרבנן *mi'd'rabbanan*, you said
נדר neder קונם *neder konam* all Kraft cheese עלי *alai*, okay, because
you knew there were some people that were מקיל *meikil* on it
and you wanted to be reinforced the fact that it was אסור
assur. *assur*, you heard stories that the רב *Rav* used to eat
Kraft cheese, so that's a no, I don't believe any of this
nonsense, קונם *konam* all Kraft cheese עלי *alai*. Okay, now it's already
אסור assur *assur* on you מדרבנן *mi'd'rabbanan*, but nevertheless it also the
נדר neder *neder* also takes effect. And now were you to eat
it, you'd also transgress your נדר neder. *neder*. Not only that, if
I now took some nice Miller's cheese and I said הרי זו
*harei zo* k'Kraft cheese, then I would be מתפיס בדבר הנדור matpis
b'davar hanadur, *matpis b'davar hanadur*, okay, just like the case of the
of the צום גדליה *Tzom Gedaliah*. And then he says והתפיסו בהן
דמתפיס בנדר הוי ואסור *v'hitpiso bahen d'matpis b'neder havei v'assur*. So אמאי
ההתפסה *amait ha-itpasa*, my נדר neder; *neder* works on something already אסור
assur, דרבנן *assur d'rabbanan*, and then if I say זה כזה *zeh
k'zeh*, then it's also מתפיס matpis בדבר הנדור b'davar hanadur, *matpis b'davar
hanadur*. Okay, there were some questions. Jonathan, you had a question before?
Why aren't these lining up? Aren't they analogous to the to the
נותר nosar *nosar* of the עולה olah, *olah*? Because because you're נותר
notar, *nosar* always, you're an אונן *onen* on the days that your
father died. Well, not on the, yeah, but an אונן *onen* isn't
אסור assur *assur*—oh, you mean because of the בשר ויין *basar v'yayin*?
You're right. You didn't say a סתם תענית *stam taanis*. The guy
said בשר ויין *basar v'yayin*. I had I had, you're right, I
was sort of thinking תענית *taanis* in my head. And תענית *taanis*
is already a תענית דרבנן *taanis d'rabbanan*. So you're right, so that's
the same type of a חידוש chiddush *chiddush*. I hadn't I hadn't
thought that through, but you're right. But that's the same type of
חידוש *chiddush* as the צום גדליה *Tzom Gedaliah*. So you're just saying,
so since this thing has a double status, why do we identify
it with the נדר neder *neder* part of it? So that is
a good point, but that's like the נותר של עולה notar shel
olah. *nosar shel olah*, is that what you just said? Right, so
okay, so that's the same חידוש *chiddush* that we said by the
נותר של עולה notar shel olah. *nosar shel olah*, that even though
it has an aspect of it that's a דבר האסור davar ha'assur
*davar ha'assur*, since it has an aspect that's a דבר הנדור davar
hanadur *davar hanadur*, we're reading the דבר הנדור davar hanadur. *davar hanadur*
as your status. So again, when it is its current status and
an aspect of it is the דבר הנדור davar hanadur, *davar hanadur*,
then it's going to be אסור assur *assur*. We're going to interpret
it in that light. The question is if the current status is
not אסור assur, *assur* as a דבר הנדור davar hanadur *davar hanadur*,
will we go back to an earlier status? That's what the question
is in סיפא *seifa*. And there you go. Can we learn infer
from this that you should be like, you know, the way you
see Shimshon common on not eating בשר ויין *basar v'yayin*? I mean,
is that—no, we should not be inferring anything about should. These are
just how, you know, people, what people did is what you infer.
Or at least it was common for people to—right, it was a
phenomenon. Yes, definitely that that we can infer. Yes. This is an
outside question, but we have a custom on ניסן *Nissan* not to
fast, right? Okay, so does that include a יארצייט *yahrtzeit* or a
תענית *taanis*? I'm not answering that question. No, because I'm wondering if
there's a difference custom here because they talk about ניסן *Nissan*. Oh,
you mean that was just the רן *Ran* gave the example of
ניסן *Nissan*. No, in the text it doesn't, the רן *Ran*—you're reading
your English, the רן *Ran* gave that example. Yeah. All right, last
question. Yes. Jonathan's point of that he mentioned בשר ויין *basar v'yayin*,
compared it to עולה *olah*, wouldn't you say that by דאורייתא *d'oraisa*
you'd be more מחמיר machmir *machmir*? No, this is—I mean, that doesn't
matter because the concept is the same. Yeah. And it's not a—whatever
the original status of it is, it's the נדר neder *neder* status
is a דאורייתא *d'oraisa* status even if the צום גדליה *Tzom Gedaliah*
was a דרבנן *d'rabbanan*, you added a נדר neder, *neder* status to
it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, אמר
אבינא תא שמע *amar Avina ta shma* כחלת אהרן *k'chalas Aharon*, okay,
we got another משנה *Mishna* coming up, I think it's משנה *Mishna*,
כחלת אהרן וכתרומתו מותר mutar *k'chalas Aharon u'k'trumaso mutar*. If you say
this is אסור assur *assur* to me like the חלה *challah* given
to the כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim* or like the תרומה truma *trumah* given
to the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*, it's מותר mutar *mutar* because even though
that's a דבר הנדור davar hanadur. *davar hanadur*, why is it a
דבר הנדור davar hanadur, *davar hanadur*, because it's a status that comes
through your verbal statement. Okay, nevertheless, it's not totally forbidden, it's מותר
mutar. *mutar* to כהנים kohanim, *Kohanim*. And so therefore it's not a
full איסור issur *issur* that derives from its דבר הנדור davar hanadur.
*davar hanadur* status. Okay, so how's that relevant? Because it only speaks
about normal תרומה truma *trumah*.
הא כתרומת לחמי תודה k'trumas lachme todah, אסור assur *ha k'trumas lachmei
todah assur*. There's another תרומה truma *trumah* which is much weightier, which
is
the תרומה truma *trumah* of לחמי תודה lachme todah; *lachmei todah*. Somebody
brings a תודה *todah*, he
brings 40 loaves of bread. 30 of them are מצה matzah *matzah*,
10 of which
are חמץ chametz *chametz*.
Okay, he waves the
whole bread with the תודה *todah*, and he gives one out of
each of the 10 loaves, right, 10 of, you know, there's three
different types of מצה matzah... *matzah*, one type of חמץ *chametz*, so
four types of loaves, 10 of each. And he gives one out
of each of those 10 to the כהן kohen *Kohen*. And that's
called תרומה truma *trumah*, the thing that's lifted up from and given
as the כהן kohen, *Kohen* of the לחמי תודה lachme todah, *lachmei
todah*. And that now is the כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim*'s and it has
a status essentially similar to תרומה truma, *trumah*. It can only be
eaten like by כהנים *Kohanim* and so on. The difference is is
that even though now its status is similar to that of תרומה
truma *trumah*, can be eaten by כהנים *Kohanim*, until the... קרבן korban.
was שחט shechted and the blood was sprinkled, it had the קדושה
kedusha of the קרבן. korban. And if somebody were to eat from
that bread before the blood was sprinkled, that would be like being,
you know, מועל moel in a קרבן. korban. Okay, so this is
an exact example of בשר זבחי שלמים לאחר זריקת הדם. Basar Zivchei
Shelamim l'achar Zrikat HaDam. You understand, the תרומה truma, of לחמי תודה;
lachmei toda by the time you only give it to the כהן
kohen, after the זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. So by the time it
becomes תרומה truma, of לחמי תודה, lachmei toda you gave it to
the כהן, kohen, it's מותר mutar to be eaten by כהנים. It's
not a דבר הנדור davar hanadur, that's אסור. assur But in its
earlier status, before the זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, it
was אסור assur,
as a דבר הנדור davar hanadur would have been an איסור מעילה.
issur me'ilah. And it sounds like when you if you were to
say, הרי זה כתרומת לחמי תודה, harei zeh k'trumas lachme todah, it
sounds like it would be אסור. assur It's only not אסור assur.
if you say הרי זה כתרומה. harei zeh k'truma. But if you
say כתרומת לחמי תודה, lachmei toda presumably it's אסור, assur. that's only
אסור assur, because you go by its earlier status. Like an עולה,
let's say. Exactly, well no, like a שלמים. shelamim. Like a שלמים
shelamim before what? The ישראל Yisrael thing. Yeah, yeah, yeah. But if
there's a כהן, kohen he
can have it, so it wouldn't be a problem.
It's not a... No, I don't know, but it's מותר mutar anyway
for ישראל. Yisrael. You mean if you said תרומת לחמי תודה, trumas
lachme todah, it might also be אסור assur. if you say מעיקרא
קמתיפס. me'ikara kamatpis. Do we understand? It's חלת אהרן. chalat Aharon. It's
מותר. mutar, It's מותר mutar, means because it's a דבר האסור Davar
ha'assur and you can't do that. Right? So no, no, no. דבר
האסור Davar ha'assur doesn't mean you're not allowed to do it. דבר
האסור davar ha'assur. means its status is something that's אסור, assur? like
בשר בחלב; basar b'chalav; it's not something that is a נדר neder
that is אסור assur. because of a נדר neder, status. But it's
אסור assur. only because you're ישראל, Yisrael, you can't eat it, but
if you're a כהן, you can eat it, right? That makes it
even less of a נדר. neder, It's not because it's אסור assur.
is why it doesn't take effect. It's even though it's אסור, assur
because it's not נדור, nadur, it doesn't take effect. It's only a
דבר האסור. davar ha'assur, If it's a דבר המותר, davar hamutar, then
of course it doesn't mean anything what you said. Okay, so the
point is even though it's a דבר האסור, davar ha'assur it doesn't
take effect because it's not a דבר הנדור. davar hanadur Now actually
תרומה truma is a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur but it's not אסור
assur מצד mitsad its נדר; neder it's not fully אסור. asur You
need both aspects: that it be a נדר and fully אסור. asur
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: ותרומת לחמי תודה לאחר זריקת דמים
היא. V'hatrumas lachme todah l'achar zrikas damim hi. תרומת לחמי תודה Trumas
lachme todah is something that right now is מותר Mutar? to כהנים
because it is after, it only exists after the זריקה. zrika. And
nevertheless it sounds like if you use that phrase it would be
אסור, asur that you would go by its status before זריקה. zrika.
So the גמרא Gemara says: אימה כתרומת הלשכה אסור. Eima k'trumas halishka
assur. No, no, no. If it says תרומת אהרן trumas Aharon
is מותר, mutar,
it doesn't mean
to
say that תרומת לחמי תודה
trumas lachme todah is אסור. asur, תרומת לחמי תודה Trumas lachme todah
would also be מותר, mutar. because you would say בהשתא קמתיפס, b'hashta
kamatpis, not בעיקרא קמתיפס. b'ikara kamatpis. So what type of a תרומה
truma would be אסור? assur. It sounds like there's a type of
a תרומה teruma, that would be אסור. assur, If you said תרומת
הלשכה, trumas halishka, donations to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Donations to
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash are always דבר הנדור davar hanadur. and
therefore are always fully מעילה me'ilah and fully אסור. assur, So the
גמרא Gemara says: One minute. אבל תרומת לחמי תודה מה? Aval trumas
lachme todah mah? What would you say if it was you if
the guy said תרומת לחמי תודה? trumas lachme todah? מותר? mutar, You'd
say it's permissible? So if that's true, that's just as permissible as
the normal תרומה, there's a much bigger חידוש to say תרומת לחמי
תודה trumas lachme todah is permissible, right? That using that phrase, because
that went actually went through a status of being a קרבן. korban,
Okay, ליתני סיפא לחמי תודה, litni seifa lachme todah, that even if
a guy said הרי זה כלחמי תודה harei zeh k'lachme todah or
הרי זה כתרומת לחמי תודה, harei zeh k'trumas lachme todah, say that
that's מותר, because even though it went through a status of being
a קרבן, korban, right now it's not אסור. assur So the גמרא
Gemara says: וכל שכן תרומתו, V'chol she'kein trumaso, and certainly just plain
old vanilla תרומה is going to be okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says: No. הא קמשמע לן תרומת לחמי תודה תרומתו היא. Ha kamashma
lan trumas lachme todah trumaso hi. It's really not הא קמשמע לן,
ha kamashma lan, but what it means is: Yeah, when we say
הרי זה כתרומת אהרן, harei zeh k'trumas Aharon, תרומת אהרן trumas Aharon
includes תרומת לחמי תודה. trumas lachme todah. We don't just mean vanilla
תרומה, we mean anything that's called תרומת אהרן. trumas Aharon. Okay, so
whether it's תרומה, תרומה that you give from the grain, whether it's
תרומת לחמי תודה, trumas lachme todah, any of these types of things
are not דבר הנדור. davar hanadur, I mean they are דבר הנדור,
davar hanadur, but they don't have an איסור issur status. Right now
they're מותר. The תרומה can be eaten by כהנים, תרומת לחמי תודה
trumas lachme todah can be eaten by כהנים. So therefore if you
said הרי זה כתרומת לחמי תודה, harei zeh k'trumas lachme todah, it
is you do not make the thing אסור assur because although it's
a דבר נדור, davar nadur, it's not אסור assur as a דבר
הנדור. davar hanadur. And therefore even though it went through a status
of being a קרבן, korban we would say בהשתא קמתיפס b'hashta kamatpis
and not בעיקרא קמתיפס. b'ikara kamatpis. Okay, clear to everybody? More or
less, as much as this can be clear. Yes? Okay, fine. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay, depends what you say. ואיבעית
אימא תרומת לחמי תודה נמי קודם זריקת דמים הוא. V'iba'is eima trumas
lachme todah nami kodem zrikas damim hu. There would be a case
that you could have תרומת לחמי תודה trumas lachme todah before זריקה.
zrika. How? You normally only separate out the one out of each
ten loaves after the זריקה. zrika. So the גמרא Gemara basically it's
going to give a more bizarre example because we have a ברייתא
braisa that talks about a more bizarre example. But it's basically very
simple: There is a scenario where I have my 40 loaves and
I separate out one of each ten and I do that separation...
designate the ones that are going to the כהן before זריקת הדם.
zrikat ha-dam. That phenomenon does exist. And now we're going to give
even a—you still can't—right. So if I said—right, that's exactly and that's
exactly the point. If I said הרי זה כתרומת לחמי תודה, harei
zeh k'terumat lachmei toda, rather than saying אה בשעתא והשתא, ah b'sha'ata
v'hashta, it's מותר, why is that a problem? It's no, since there's
a scenario of תרומת לחמי תודה terumat lachmei toda that is that
is אסור assur. right now—תרומת לחמי תודה לפני זריקת דם—that's terumat lachmei
toda lifnei zrikat dam how we're going to interpret it. You know
what that's like? When the guy said הרי זה נותר harei zeh
notar and we're going to interpret it as נותר notar של עולה,
shel olah right? So it's very interesting. We're prepared to interpret it
in a particular way that
is actually אסור assur even though it's unusual, that makes it the
איסור category, but that's as long as we can get that to
be the current status. We're not going to—but we might still resist
interpreting it based on an earlier status. So if your words can
refer to something in its current status that's אסור assur? as a
דבר הנדור, davar hanadur. we'll fit them into it. So if you
said נותר, we'll say what you meant is נותר של עולה. If
you said—if you said—כי סתם נדרים להחמיר. ki stam nedarim l'hachmir.
If you're—because that's the whole point of how do we interpret what
your words mean if we don't have enough information? So we'll give
it the most מחמיר interpretation. Okay, but maybe there are limits. So
here what we're saying is, as long as it's based on its
current status, we'll give it the strictest reading possible. נותר means נותר
של עולה. לחמי תודה lachmei toda, means לחמי תודה לפני זריקת הדם
lachmei toda lifnei zrikat ha-dam or תרומת לחמי תודה terumat lachmei toda
means לפני זריקת הדם. lifnei zrikat ha-dam. But if what we had
to do was say now there's no read we can give
of it right now that would make it אסור, what we would
have to do to interpret your words as a דבר הנדור davar
hanadur, is refer to the status of an object that it had
earlier, that maybe we're not prepared to do. That's our question of
מעיקרא mei'ikara or בהשתא. b'hashta. So what we're saying to answer some
of these questions is, yeah, maybe we say בהשתא b'hashta but we
are prepared to give it a—find an unusual scenario of בהשתא. b'hashta.
That we would be prepared to do but we wouldn't necessarily be
prepared to go to an earlier status. דאפרשינהו בלישה d'aphrashinhu b'lisha means
when you're still kneading. We haven't said those words yet. Okay, so
no, you're reading ahead. Okay, so נמי קודם זריקה הוא nami kodem
zrika hu כגון—we k'gon didn't get to the כגון. k'gon. So כגון
דאפרשינהו בלישה. k'gon d'aphrashinhu b'lisha. Now we're going to—now we said the
words. Now we're going to go to an even stranger case than
just that you took the loaves of bread before the זריקה. zrika.
That's really not so strange. I mean, it's not common, but you
bake the bread, you have your forty loaves of bread and you
just designate the one out of each ten before the זריקת הדם.
zrikat ha-dam. But now we're going to go to an even weirder
scenario just to show you how early in the stage you can
do this—that you could even designate the לחמי תודה when it's still
dough, when you're kneading it. One minute. כי הא דאמר רבי טובי
בר קיסנא אמר שמואל—again ki ha d'amar Rabi Tuvi bar Kisna amar
Shmuel שמואל Shmuel is coming up—לחמי תודה שאפאה בארבע חלות, lachmei toda
she'afa'an b'arba chalot, if you made your loaves of bread—you did not
make forty loaves, you made four loaves, each loaf because there are
four separate types, so you can't make any fewer than four. But
each loaf was the size of ten loaves. Okay, so you made
four humongous challah loaves, okay? So of these forty loaves of bread—and
instead of forty, you made four, each one the size of ten.
יצא, yatza, you've fulfilled your obligation. So then it says one minute.
והכתיב ארבעים? v'haktiv arba'im? You're supposed to have forty! למצוה, l'mitzvah, that's
only לכתחילה. l'chatchila. והבא למשקל תרומה, v'haba l'mishkal teruma, but one minute,
you have to take one out of each ten. וכי תימא דשקיל
חדא ריפתא אכולה, v'chi teima d'shakil chada rifta akula, maybe one of
the four
counts for the other even though it's not ten percent. והתנן אחד
מכל קרבן, v'hatnan echad mikol korban, you take one out of each
of them, each group as a קרבן korban as a gift, you
know, as an offering, שלא יטול מקרבן על חבירו, shelo yitol mikorban
al chaveiro, that you can't take from one type of loaf on
the other type, right?
There are four separate types, and from each type you have to
take a gift—right, you have to separate לחמי תודה from each type.
וכי תימא דשקיל פרוסה, v'chi teima d'shakil prusa, fine, break off a
piece of this giant loaf and have that be the לחמי תודה,
the תרומה, excuse me, מכל חד וחד mikol chad v'chad from each
one.
והתנן אחד שלא יטול
פרוסה,
v'hatnan
echad shelo yitol
prusa, you can't take a partial. So even if you said that
in theory you could make four gigantic loaves instead of forty, how
do you do the תרומת לחמי תודה? terumat lachmei toda?
There's no way to do that. אלא, ela, the only way to
do it is דאפרשינהו בלישה. d'aphrashinhu b'lisha. So what you do is
you separate it off while you're still kneading it.
דשקיל חדא מחמץ וחדא מן החלות,
d'shakil
chada mechometz
v'chada min hachalot,
you take one
out of the חמץ
doughs and one out of each of the other מצה doughs—אחת מן
החלות ואחת מן הרקיקין
ואחת מן הרבוכה.
achat min hachalot
v'achat min harekikin v'achat min harevocha.
Those are the three other types. And therefore what do you do?
So here you have—well, the way the ר"ן says it, although it's
not so clear, is what I'm doing is I knead it and
I made my ten מצה...
loaves here, and I take one of these in dough, and I
put it aside, and then I take the remaining nine, and then
I mix
them all together, and from
those make one big giant loaf. Okay, or I have my ten
רבוכה revucha loaves and I take one and I put it aside
and then I take what's remaining and I make it a giant
one. All right, so that's all very interesting. Fine, but the point
for us is just to demonstrate how early in the process it's
possible to take the תרומת לחמי תודה. terumas lachmei todah. Even in
a bizarre scenario you can even take it when it's dough, and
you can certainly take it after it's been baked before זריקת הדם,
zrikas hadam, and that will be effective. It's not a normal thing
to do, but it'll be effective. So therefore once again, the גמרא
Gemara says if somebody said הרי זה כתרומת לחמי תודה, harei zeh
k'terumas lachmei todah, if we're going to assume that that is מתפיס
בדבר הנדור, the question is but one minute, תרומת לחמי תודה terumas
lachmei todah is no longer אסור. Doesn't that show you that
דביקרא קמתפיס? d'beikara kamatpis?
And it says no, cause there's a scenario of תרומת לחמי תודה
terumas lachmei todah even right now that is אסור, a תרומת לחמי
תודה
terumas lachmei todah that was taken before זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. Okay,
so we'll interpret your words
in a way that makes it currently a דבר הנדור davar hanadur
that's אסור, but we might not be prepared to go back to
an earlier status. All right, so we still don't have an answer
to our question, דביקרא קמתפיס d'beikara kamatpis or דהשתא קמתפיס. d'hashta kamatpis.
Next case. Okay, רבי יהודה מתיר. Rabbi Yehuda matir. So I'm sorry,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. לימא כתנאי. leima kitna'ei. Let's
say this is like a debate of תנאים. tannaim. הרי עלי כבכור.
harei alai k'bechor. This loaf of bread is אסור to
me like a בכור.
bechor. Now, a בכור bechor is very interesting because I mean I'm
going to give away the punchline, but I'll give it away, because
a בכור bechor is it a דבר הנדור davar hanadur. or not?
Where does a בכור bechor get its קדושה kedusha from? When it's
born? When it's born. So it's actually one of the, a קרבן
korban that you don't need to say anything, it's the one קרבן
korban that you don't need to be מקדיש, makdish, it's just automatically
is קדוש kadosh from the time that it's born. However, there is
a מצוה mitzvah to say תקדיש, takdish, as the פסוק pasuk says
תקדיש לה' אלהיך, takdish l'Hashem Elokecha, that when it says that you
should sanctify your בכור. bechor. So in addition to its natural קדושה,
kedusha, you also instill קדושה kedusha into it when you sanctify it.
So if you say הרי זה כבכור, harei zeh k'bechor, are you
being מתפיס something בדבר הנדור, because it's possible to have a נדר
status if you sanctify it, or maybe even if you did sanctify
it, since its basic status of a קרבן korban, didn't require your
הקדשה, hakdasha, it always just remains a דבר האסור davar ha'assur. and
not a דבר הנדור. davar hanadur. Okay, so that's the fascinating question
by בכור. bechor. So הרי עלי כבכור. harei alai k'bechor. רבי יעקב
אוסר ורבי יהודה מתיר, Rabbi Yaakov osser v'Rabbi Yehuda matir, debate or
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, debate of whether it's אסור or not. היכי
דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא לפני זריקת דמים, ileima lifnei
zrikas damim, if you said this is like a בכור bechor before
there's been a זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam, מאי טעמא דמאן דשרי? mai
ta'ama d'man d'shari? Why do you permit? Now I already gave you
the answer to that, but the גמרא Gemara says assuming a בכור
bechor is a קרבן, korban so why should it of course it
should be אסור if it's its status before זריקת דם. zrikas dam.
אלא לאחר זריקת דם, ela l'achar zrikas dam, if it's after the
זריקת דם, zrikas dam, מאי טעמא דמאן דאסר? mai ta'ama d'man d'assar?
Why should it be forbidden? You can eat a בכור bechor after
זריקת דם. zrikas dam. אלא
לאו, ela lav, it must be the case just like our שלמים
shlamim case, top of יג עמוד א, yud gimmel amud aleph, דמנח
בשר בכור, d'manach basar bechor, that right in front of you is
the meat of a בכור bechor after זריקת דם, zrikas hadam, obviously
it's meat, ומנח בשר דהיתרא גביה, u'manach basar d'heteira gabeih, and some
other meat is in front of you or דהיתרא, d'heteira, right? Or
let's say a loaf of bread, ואמר זה כזה, v'amar zeh kazeh,
this loaf of bread is like this steak here from this בכור,
bechor, this lamb chop, okay, וכתנאי, v'kitna'ei, and it's a debate of
תנאים, tannaim, whether you go by its current status which is היתר,
heter, or you go by its original status before it was שחט
shachted and זריקת הדם zrikas hadam where it was אסור. So maybe
that's exactly this debate of דמעיקרא d'mei'ikara or דהשתא. d'hashta. גמרא says
לא, lo, no, not necessarily, דכולי עלמא לפני זריקת דמים, d'chulei alma
lifnei zrikas damim, we could be talking about that the sheep is
a בכור bechor and it's still walking around and alive. So why
doesn't everybody agree that's a problem? It's קדושת קרבן, kedushas korban, it's
totally אסור at this state if it's not זריקת דם. zrikas dam.
ומה השתא? u'ma hashta? So it should be חל chal because it's
a קרבן korban before זריקת דם. zrikas dam. ומאי טעמא דמאן דשרי?
u'mai ta'ama d'man d'shari? אמר קרא, amar kra, כי ידור, ki yiddor,
כי ידור נדר לה' אלהיך, ki yiddor neder l'Hashem Elokecha, עד שידור
בדבר הנדור, ad sheyiddor b'davar hanadur, that's our basic principle, it has
to be with a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur. something that got its
status through a נדר, through a verbal act, לאפוקי בכור דדבר האסור
הוא, le'apokei bechor d'davar ha'assur hu, a בכור bechor is not a
דבר הנדור, it's a דבר האסור. davar ha'asur What does that mean?
For the reason I said: it did not get its status through
your verbal act of sanctifying it. ומאן דאסר, u'man d'assar, so okay,
so what about the one that says it's אסור? אמר קרא, amar
kra, he's got a פסוק, pasuk, לה', l'Hashem, כי ידור נדר לה',
ki yiddor neder l'Hashem, לרבות דבר האסור. l'rabos davar ha'assur. Now it
doesn't really mean לרבות דבר האסור, l'rabos davar ha'assur, what, we're going
to throw out everything we've been learning for the past two weeks?
That oh no you don't need a דבר נדור, davar nadur, you
could say הרי זה כבשר בחלב? harei zeh k'basar b'chalav? No, of
course not. What it really means is לרבות בכור, l'rabos bechor, that
even though a בכור bechor has its status without your word, since,
well one thing we're going to say is you add, you can
add your קדושה, kedusha, but you could say even more simply: it's
part of a class of קרבנות korbanos that normally the status of
קדושה kedusha of a קרבן is something that normally is through a
דבר הנדור. בכור bechor might get it in other ways, but its
basic status of קדושת קרבן kedushas korban is a דבר הנדור. That
would be one way of understanding it. In other words, it's sort
of like implicitly a הקדוש ברוך הוא... hakadosh baruch hu... Others would
have to say that, but conceptually, all right, Israel somehow... Well, right,
that is true that it does become קדוש. kadosh. Anyway, we're going
to say because of the קדושה kedusha you add to it, but
I don't know if we have to say that right now. Right
now we could just be saying that the extra ריבוי ribuy of
נדר לה' Neder Lashem is that even some things that get their
קדושה kedusha by themselves, if they're in a class of דבר הנדור,
also are in this category. One minute. ומאן דשרי U'man d'shari so
the one that says that it's still permissible לה' מאי עביד ליה?
Lashem mai avid leh? What does he do with the extra words
לה'? Lashem? מיבעי ליה למתפיס בחטאת ואשם. Mibay'leh l'matfis b'chatas v'asham. That
a חטאת chatas and an אשם. asham. Why do you need a
special פסוק? pasuk? Because although they get their קדושה kedusha through your
words, they're not a fully דבר הנדור because they don't come through
your free will, right? You're obligated. So again, a classic נדר is
somebody saying, like, you know, וידר יעקב נדר לאמר, Vayidar Yaakov neder
lemor, God, I'm going to offer this to you. It's something that
you're offering to God. So maybe we would have defined עד שיתפיס
בדבר הנדור ad she'yatfis b'davar hanadur so narrowly that it's not just
a status that you created with your words, but a status that
you freely created with your words. And only a free offering, only
if you said
הרי זה כעולה, harei zeh k'olah, הרי זה כשלמים. harei zeh k'shlamim.
But a חטאת chatas or an אשם, asham, which comes through an
obligation, maybe not? So no, we don't really, we're bracketing that aspect
of the נדר, that free will offering aspect of the נדר, we're
focusing on the status that came to it through the words. So
לרבות חטאת ואשם. ולהוציא את הבכור. l'rabos chatas v'asham u'lehotzi es habechor?
Okay, that's right. ומה ראית, U'mah ra'isa, what motivated you, לרבות חטאת
ואשם l'rabos chatas v'asham. ולהוציא את הבכור? u'lehotzi es habechor. What's the
difference? מרבה אני חטאת ואשם שהוא מתפיסו בנדר. Marbeh ani chatas v'asham
shehu matfiso b'neder. Yes, חטאת chatas and אשם asham come from an
obligation, but the status of the animal that when you sanctify it
comes through your words.
ומוציא אני את הבכור שהוא קדוש ממעי אמו,
U'motzi
ani es
habechor shehu kadosh mei-imei imo, that its status does not come through
your words,
the status it's already sanctified from the mother's womb.
Okay, so that's a very strong argument, so it's not a דבר
הנדור.
ומאן דאסר, U'man d'asar, the one that says it's forbidden, and
here's where I think we do a shift, we could
have just said it's
a class of קרבנות korbanot and that's enough. But no, he says
even a בכור bechor has a status through your words.
בכור נמי מתפיסו בנדר הוא.
Bechor
nami matfiso b'neder hu.
A בכור bechor also comes through your words. דתניא משום רבי אמרו
מנין לנולד בכור בתוך ביתו שמצוה להקדישו, D'tanya, mishum Rebbi amru, minayin
lenolad bechor betoch beiso she'mitzvah lehakdisho, even though the animal is born
as a בכור bechor and is already קדוש, kadosh, you have an
obligation to be מקדיש makdish it and to add your קדושה, kedusha,
שנאמר הזכר תקדיש, shene'emar hazachar takdish, you should sanctify. ומאן דשרי, U'man
d'shari, and the one who responds back, כי לא מקדיש ליה
מי לא מיקדש,
ki
lo makdish leh
mi lo mikdash, יישר כח, shkoach, you're supposed to sanctify it, but
even
without your sanctity it has its own sanctity by itself.
So therefore the fundamental sanctity of a בכור bechor is not through
your נדר and it's a דבר האסור and not a דבר הנדור.
Now what's interesting
is that the one who
says that it still points out that it still has
the sanctity, but
it's not like he denies that your sanctifying of it might add
a level of קדושה kedusha or might add something, but it's still
not the central identity of the object, it's some, you know, something
well right and something that's not necessary and therefore its basic identity
is not a דבר הנדור. This is important and the Rav Soloveitchik
used to like very much use this as an important model of
thinking about the nature of קידוש kiddush on שבת, Shabbos, where he
basically said שבת Shabbos has קדושה kedusha by itself, but קידוש, kiddush,
what's our קידוש? kiddush?
Our קידוש kiddush could just be acknowledging its קדושה, kedusha, recognizing it,
declaring it, but he I think there's a ראשון rishon that basically
based himself on that made this comparison already and he said we
have a מצוה mitzvah to add our own קדושה, kedusha, our words
like by the בכור, bechor, they're not just words, they actually yes
it's true
even without our קידוש kiddush שבת Shabbos is קדוש, kadosh,
without our קידוש kiddush the בכור bechor is קדוש, kadosh, but when
we're מקדיש makdish it we add that human aspect of קדושה kedusha
to it as well, right, and that becomes part of the קדושה
kedusha of שבת Shabbat or the act of קידוש, kiddush, that's how
he wanted to see the מצוה mitzvah of making קידוש kiddush on
שבת Shabbos is actually the adding of a human level of קדושה
kedusha to the already divinely given קדושה. kedusha. So we'll with that
we will enter into שבת, Shabbat, we'll end before שבת. Shabbos. Yes,
יישר כח. shkoach. That's a fundamentally mystical idea. Yeah, I guess so.